This is Software Engineering Radio, the podcast for professional developers on the web at se-radio.net.
SE Radio is brought to you by the IEEE Computer Society and by IEEE Software Magazine,
online at computer.org/software.
Welcome to Software Engineering Radio. I'm your host Brijesh Ammanath.
Today, we will be discussing privacy and security of AI coding assistants with our guest Luke Hinds.
Luke is the CTO of Stack Lock.
He created Sixstore while a distinguished engineer at Red Hat.
He's a security thought leader, engineer, public speaker who loves building open-source software and communities,
as well as leading talented engineering teams to develop innovative, cutting-edge security technologies at scale.
Luke, is there anything I missed that you would like to add to your introduction?
No, you pretty much covered it all there. Yeah, and in a very succinct and on point.
Thanks.
Luke, if you can start off by explaining the increased role of AI coding agents in improving program.
productivity. Certainly.
So, this really harks back to 2017 when the paper came out of Google around the Transformers architecture.
The paper was called Attention is all that you need.
It's speaking about the attention mechanism.
Prior to then, we'd had AI machine learning have been around for quite some time,
but we hadn't really seen any killer applications of it beyond statistical analysis.
and people would use it as a business tool essentially.
And so, we started to see these sort of general-purpose models come out.
And then quite early on, there was of course GitHub Copilot.
And this is where it was quite astonishing really.
Even though the quality was not quite there,
the ability for these machines to generate code, it was noticed.
as being a very clear emerging use case application of these models was how good they were at. generating code.
And initially, we started off with a system called fill in the middle.
And fill in the middle is auto completion of code.
And what happens is the code is generated based on the prepend and the append.
So, the content that surrounds the prompt, or effectively where the cursor is situated within a IDE.
Okay, so the prompt would fill up the code that's above, say 10 lines,
and the 10 lines below the cursor.
And then the model would have to predict what is in the middle.
So, it was called fill in the middle.
FIM is the term that they use.
So, I think this was one of the first times.
that we started to see AI really start to get some traction with software engineers.
And you got this auto complete magical to complete functionality that came around.
And that was really where there would have definitely been a marked increase in productivity for people.
that were using that.
because as a software engineer, there would be a lot of tasks that you would perform.
where you wouldn't really need to exercise any level of really pushing your brain to the limits.
There would be things such as hashing out structs and setting up functions,
and just sort of general housekeeping type tasks.
And AI proved to be very good at doing that.
I remember when I started to use Copilot myself,
I was quite surprised at how it would understand precisely the response format.
that I would need to set out.
for a struct or it would somehow magically understand what I needed for a JSON structure.
And this is where we really started to see, I think, a productivity increase was.
In a lot ways, it was a tool as a developer tool,
in much the same way as when shells started to become more purposed to developers.
and you started to get that sort of rich experience within a terminal.
And people made them very much their own thing because it improved their productivity essentially.
And that was the start of the productivity gain that has happened within software development.
I think there is a lot more future applications of AI.
that will increase productivity and will help a lot to reduce churn.
It will take away the grind of a lot of stuff that engineers have had to do,
they've had to live with and accept.
I think we'll start to see AI factor those way over time as well.
All right.
You've covered GitHub Copilot in one of our previous episodes, 533.
I'll make sure we'll link it to that.
Have any studies been done to quantify the improved productivity by using AI coding assistance?
Yes, there are.
Now, people have different views as to how accurate they are,
but one of the ones that I heard was it was related to GitHub.
and it was around the region of 45 to 50%.
I cannot remember the exact figure now,
but there's quite a substantial claim that productivity had been significantly raised through the use of AI.
That's quite a large number.
Certainly it certainly is.
And we have noticed a marked ability to be able to move more quickly with what we build,
thank you to AI.
So, I'm part of a startup and we use AI very effectively for prototyping.
Okay, so we wouldn't really trust it in a large code base.
It just doesn't handle large code bases so well,
but when you very quickly want to prototype and build something, that's where AI is exceptionally strong.
To move from zero to something you can act very quickly.
and that's very useful in a fast-moving environment such as a startup.
where you need to quickly validate ideas, you need to connect up and integrate different systems,
and AI can be great there cuz you just want to see something wiggle.
You want to see something working.
You want to prove the hypothesis to yourself.
And that's where I found I I've really embraced AI myself is to do a lot of tasks.
where I need to move fast, I need to be reactive,
I want to try something out, I want to validate something.
That is where AI's really come into its own.
For myself and some of the engineers that I have in my company working on producing software.
And what are the key risks introduced due to the reliance on AI coding assistance?
So, there are many.
Okay, some of them are old risks within the new world.
We looked at coding assistance and did some studies on their security.
What are the risks?
And I think one of the clear ones that would became immediately present was data exfiltration,
even if unwillingly.
The leakage of secrets, tokens, passwords, personal information.
Essentially, coding assistants, they rely on context.
Context is really important.
So, context is essentially snippets of code.
They need to understand the entire or at least a section of a syntax tree within code,
so that they can make changes without breaking other functions or methods.
that belong to a particular class that they're working within.
So, they like to grab entire files. That's one of the things you'll see quite often.
when you're working with a coding assistant such as Cursor.
or Copilot, they will take a whole file via the IDE, they'll load it into a prompt,
and then that prompt will then be sent to an endpoint.
where it'll be canonicalized and serialized and put into a format.
that the LLM can then make a prediction around what the task is at hand.
It'll start to generate code.
And quite often, these files can be it could be cryptographic keys,
they could be.env files where people have database passwords and perhaps for a production site. It could be API tokens.
Quite often, I spoke about earlier being able to prototype very quickly,
that's one of the useful things for AI.
We've all done it as software engineers.
You are writing a single script.
You want to see an API work.
You hardcode the token in because you know you're not going to push it to GitHub.
You're certainly not going to deploy it, but you just want to see the thing work.
So, you take a token and you hardcode it.
And those effectively are captured by the IDE and they're all sent out.
And these keys are I mean, it's you could discuss the receiving party could be trusted.
Could be a large corporation, Microsoft Azure or Anthropic or wherever the cloud service is running.
They may well be entities that you should never leak keys,
but they're not likely to exploit you by receiving those keys.
But I think the other concern is.
that quite often the data that is received is used to train models.
So, hypothetically, it's not too far-fetched to have a scenario.
where a large language model may spit out a token that it's learned during its training phase.
It could spit out a password.
It could spit out a bit of personal information.
You may have a spreadsheet that you by accident put within a folder.
that contains code and that could be picked up by the IDE.
and it could have payslip information, social security numbers, medical information.
And this data can then be used for reinforcement learning.
It can be used to train the model because data is king effectively.
Data is the key value that is derived from a lot of these services.
So, those are the key risks I think for developers is that it's very easy to leak information.
For the actual models themselves, I think some of the other risks are quite often they have a. distant training dates.
Okay, so knowledge is a model is tuned.
and the knowledge is recent at the point of where that training happens.
Right. Now, afterwards, knowledge becomes stale effectively.
So, it's at a certain point in time. It's a snapshot in time.
And because these models are very expensive to do full training,
it's not something that happens every week or month, even.
Sometimes it can be months that will go by.
A model will be in circulation, and then the next new frontier model will come out.
And during that time, security risks can happen. Okay?
Packages can become malicious, maintainer accounts can be overtaken, vulnerabilities can be discovered, critical vulnerabilities.
And the large language model will have no implicit knowledge of that because of its training cutoff date.
So, there is a chance that a model could recommend dangerous content, effectively.
You know, it could introduce security risks into your code.
because it doesn't have that current knowledge that it is a risk.
I guess one way of highlighting this is we remember Log4j. Okay?
This is sort of way before the current batch of large language models.
and the transformer architecture was in public use.
But you imagine a model had been trained, say a week before Log4j,
and then the next new model would not come out for 4 or 5 months later.
It could quite easily be creating people's dependency files for when they want to create a Java project,
and then in there is Log4j, effectively.
So, yeah, I'd say stale knowledge cutoffs are one of the things.
that we look to do in Stack Clock was that we use an embeddings model.
and a retrieval-augmented generation system to bring in the latest threat intelligence around what's dangerous, malicious, archived, deprecated,
and so forth.
So, there are ways that you can get more fresh, recent information in there.
The other, as I said, is is leaking.
That's something else that we've also looked to address on the tail end of our research.
And in general, just hallucinations.
Models will come out with functions that do not exist.
It will be sketching out some code that uses an upstream library, a dependency,
and it will just make up names.
It will come out with function names that don't exist.
And there is a chance that if that's happening at a high frequency,
then somebody could attempt to kind of squat on these hallucinated names and weaponize them.
So, those are some of the key risks.
And I mean, there are other things such as prompt injections and insecure models.
Models have, you know, they use PyTorch and you've got.
It's not used so much now, but pickle,
which was susceptible to various attacks, and they started to use something called safe tensors,
which is a lot more safer.
now around the execution of code, but I would say those are the key aspects, the key security concerns.
All right, quite a few key points over there,
and we will double click on two of them specifically.
One is secrets management, and the other one is dependency injection in this session.
It's a good leeway into the next theme of the podcast, which is around secrets management.
You've elaborated on what kind of secrets could be leaked,
but what risk does the passage of secrets to LLMs pose?
Is it primarily that once it's used in training, it could be exposed?
Or are there other risks because of LLMs having that secrets within its context?
I guess it would be who receives the secret.
Okay, so there are some organizations, corporations that we're going to feel a level of trust towards.
If they're a large business that has a reputation,
why would they want to use an individual's key to exploit a system? It's not very likely to happen.
Mhm. So, I would say with these large vendors that have these frontier models,
the risk is much likely going to be that the large language model regurgitates a secret. or a key that it's discovered.
Now, if you were to use a provider who is less well established, does not have a brand.
that they're going to be very protective of,
does not have a core business that's financially lucrative enough.
that they don't need to resort to nefarious malicious actions, then.
that could be a risk.
I mean, this was one of the things that people,
perhaps rightly or wrongly, inferred for Deep Seek when they put up an API.
I have absolutely no opinion myself there.
People were effectively saying, you know, your secrets are being leaked to a company.
which operates outside of the jurisdiction of where most software engineers and companies tend to operate.
So, I'm actually not insinuating anything at all there myself.
The Deep Seek people seem like very bright, smart people,
but there was this element of if these models are the inference points are much wider.
and there are many more providers, then.
obviously your secrets are going to be leaked to many more APIs, many more cloud services.
They're going to be stored in many more logs and monitoring systems and so forth.
And so, somebody effectively with bad intentions could possibly exfiltrate those secrets and use them.
And how easy is it for malicious actors to extract secrets or secret data from LLMs?
Is it through prompt engineering or are there other methods they use?
It would be through prompt engineering.
I would say it's not easy.
It would require probably a prompt injection attack to get the large language model to break out of. its safeguards.
So, large language models are trained so that they have a set of guardrails around.
There's certain dialogue that they will not enter that consists of physical harm or hate and so forth.
And security is another one of them.
If you ask a lot of large language models,
tell me how to write a Bitcoin miner or tell me how to write a script.
that exploits somebody's computer, it will refuse.
It has its guardrails.
But, they can be broken out of this.
There's a sequence of words that we'll use which will allow them to drop all of that context,
that protection.
And that is when you could no doubt likely get them to reveal some of what they've ingested.
I must admit, it's not something I've achieved myself or I've done myself,
but prompt injections are not as difficult as you would imagine.
Recently when our Gemini came out, I found one myself.
that allowed me to break the model completely out of its sort of safe controls.
And that is a concern, effectively, is people break the system outside of its guard rails,
and then it could start to reveal some of that information.
Have there been known cases where secrets have been leaked due to AI-generated code? Any examples come to mind?
Have been leaked from the large language model or from a user's environment?
Due to use of AI-generated code.
I don't know of a large language model in the wild generating code that uses a secret, that like a cryptographic token.
I imagine there's probably quite a few passwords out there, but it's not something I've seen myself.
Okay, so nothing like the Log4j example, which was before LLMs and before AI-generated code. Nothing major has hit the news.
Not as yet, but I have a feeling something large will arrive.
I don't know of any particular attack that's about to manifest, but I'm pretty sure we'll see one quite soon.
Hopefully not. Fingers crossed. Yes, yeah.
Are there best practices developers can follow.
when using AI-generated coding assistance beyond just secret scanning and package validation?
Yes.
So, it's very easy to switch off when AI's generating code.
Now, people all have a different propensity to how much they do that,
but there's this they call it vibe coding, which is.
where you essentially let the AI just keep spinning.
You auto approve everything and you allow an AI just have unfettered access to building an application.
I'd say the more tighter that you can review the code that AI generates, the better.
It's much more likely that if you read the code,
you scrutinize the code, you're going to notice certain patterns that are insecure,
certain ways that code can be generated.
where if you really look at it,
you'll start to see very simple sort of top 10 OWASP type risks that could be introduced.
Shell execution, unsanitized input is one that I see quite often LLMs will generate.
So, always try to sort of stay close to your code.
Try not to switch off too much.
and let it just have free reign to generate what it wants.
Most senior engineers will will probably be nodding heads going, "Oh, yeah.
Tell me something new."
But, something that's very key, I think,
as newer engineers start to come in.
and start to use these tools as as more of a first go-to approach, effectively.
I'd say that's one of the key things.
And then around information leakage awareness, really.
Be aware that anything that's within that folder is likely to be leaked.
So, use environment variables, of course, for secrets.
Or even better, use a proper cryptographic system.
where you have something like Vault or even a hardware security module or a YubiKey.
Or you start to leverage these technologies.
so that the secrets are not in the code in the first place.
And then there's also CodeGate, which is something that StackLok we built.
It's an open source project which will provide those protections for you.
You won't even know that you've been at risk of leaking something cuz it will be redacted on. the fly.
So, we use lots of technology to to sense secrets leak.
And that's a free to use open source project that anybody can use with their coding assistance.
Why are existing productions like.gitignore or cursor ignore not enough.
I think really because environments I don't know those systems too well,
but the truth is that when AI is operating on code I mean code is forever changing.
It's like a get ignore could be good to stop you accidentally checking secrets into your GitHub repository.
You could put a dot M file in there.
You could kind of block these things from being pushed to a repo.
I'm not too aware of the dot cursor rules whether they allow to block secrets or not.
But quite often it's not very deterministic where you're going to put tokens,
where you're going to put keys.
You know, if you accidentally get a medical report in your Gmail,
you do save as in the browser.
You forgot that the last time you used the save as feature was to download an image.
that you wanted to use on a website.
And oops, I've saved as my medical report.
It's gone into my code repo folder.
and now it's being grabbed by the IDE and sent up to the cloud.
I would say things are too arbitrary really to rely on a having to constantly update a text. file on your system.
Agreed.
So get ignore or cursor ignore is more about stopping the file being checked in and not from.
I believe so, yeah.
Like I said, I'm not too aware of the dot cursor what they're doing there,
but if it is like get ignore.
and it stops the IDE from processing the file.
Like I'd say things are a lot more transient really.
They're not as fixed that I think that that would be a suitable protection system.
Right. What techniques does Code Gate use to ensure that secrets are not accidentally leaked?
So we do several things.
For personal information, we actually use system been in part of machine learning for a.
while near entity recognition.
So we have a small model which is able to recognize credit card numbers,
medical numbers, social security numbers, personal details, phone numbers, emails, any sort of PII.
This model is able to effectively match quite well.
We also have forms of sensing technology for keys and passwords.
So, we use entropy detection, different systems there to see.
that something is likely to be a password or a cryptographic token, an API key.
We leverage these machine learning techniques to be able to pattern match effectively sensitive materials.
And then what we do in CodeGate, CodeGate is effectively an inline system.
So, when you converse with an LLM, you're actually using RESTful APIs.
Okay, so it's like any other application.
Your coding assistant is a client.
It will take content, the code, or perhaps if you've typed something into a chat box,
it will take that content and it will load it into a JSON payload.
which will be posted to a REST API where the payload will be processed,
a response will come back, and it's very much that typical sort of RESTful flow. that we're all used to.
And so, what we are able to do is capture this payload as it comes through CodeGate on.
its way to the LLM inference point.
and then we scrutinize it, we check it for secrets.
On the return path, we check it for malicious packages,
and we effectively are able to trace these things on transit, okay?
But, the key thing with CodeGate is this happens locally on your machine.
So, it's not like we're a kind of an EDR endpoint.
where you're just sending your secrets to someone else.
This is processed right on your machine, and that information never it your machine.
So, if we pick up that there is a cryptographic token within the prompt payload, what we do is we redact it.
So, we swap that token, let's say it's an API token, for a unique string. Okay?
And that payload then goes off to the LLM, which may well refactor the code.
It could move the lines around.
And then it comes back as a response. As it.
When it comes back as a response,
we receive it, we match the placeholder,
the nominator of where that secret has been redacted with this particular randomly generated string. that we have.
And then we swap it back.
We put the secret back in.
So, that when the code appears in your IDE, you can see your API token there. Okay?
And so, what effectively has happened is it's been redacted on the fly.
And we do this with all personal information as well.
If somebody was to accidentally send a file or a file was to be sent to an LLM.
and it contains a credit card number, we would redact it on the fly.
Out it goes, goes to the LLM.
The LLM does whatever it needs to do, refactor it, fix a bug.
The content comes back.
And then in line, we switch back the redacted string to the cryptographic token.
or password or credit card number.
And then it appears back in your IDE.
But we also decorate the prompt so that via the code in the system,
we'll give a warning and we'll say, "There was a credit card number. that was found in your prompt.
We actually protected that for you so you don't have to take any further action,
but you should perhaps be aware of why this is a risk.
and here are some best practices that you can implement."
We're just using standard machine learning technologies here to provide these protections.
We do something similar with malicious packages.
We have a database of malicious packages that we've created over the years in Stack Club. Uh we also run our own SCA system.
We we our own threat hunters that report packages as being malicious or,
you know, deprecated, no longer archived.
And if we see the LLM recommend one of these to the coding assistant, what we do is as soon as we see something.
that looks like a package name, we have a vectorized database and an embeddings model,
and we do a similarity search around that name to see.
if it matches anything within our vulnerability database.
If it does, then we're able to flag.
that to the user before they run pip install or npm install and end up backdooring their machine.
So, we do similarity search because sometimes uh there can be typo squatting attacks as well,
and that allows us to sense that those are happening.
So, yeah, with CodeGate you you get all of these controls locally in your machine.
You get the ability to redact any personal information or secrets, but your code still comes back refactored.
It doesn't disturb your your flow, effectively.
Your development flow is unhindered.
You don't have to take any action.
We just inform you that we've covered your back and that we redacted the secrets and the tokens. And.
And likewise, if the LLM recommends any malicious packages or suspicious packages,
we're able to raise alert of that.
And we provide all these protections in line and within the safe confines of your machine. Nothing ever leaves your machine.
I think that's all a very clever way of doing things.
So, redacting or replacing that secret information or personal information with something else,
so that the flow of programmer is not impacted.
I think that's very key. That's correct. Yeah, very much.
Because, you know, one of one of the things I found being a security engineer,
somebody that's always been focused on developing security technologies.
that will be adopted by engineers, people want to be productive.
And if security is something that hinders them,
blocks them, slows them down, they're much less likely to adopt it.
So, for security to be successful with developers,
it's it's got to be as seamless as possible because there's always some new shiny framework.
or API that's got their attention that's going to make them more productive.
Whereas security you don't want them to have to learn about why they should protect themselves against a. particular threat.
and then have them go through a a long protracted set of steps to implement the security to. then be blocked.
and to want to turn it off cuz it's frustrating.
It's just the not the right way to get developers to embrace security is to make it a.
a difficult experience.
If you can make it seamless, they're much more likely to adopt it.
I mean, that's one of the things we found with six store.
when we were trying to get developers to adopt best practices around signing software.
Up until that point it had been quite a a painful frustrating experience.
People were worried about how to manage the keys. Did they need specialist hardware?
How would they rotate keys?
You know, it was these tools that were quite dated like PGP,
GPG and it was just a frustrating experience for developers.
So with six store what we got right was we made it very very easy to sign effectively,
you know, it's very very minimal effort required from the developer.
So it almost be seamless and that's why we got the adoption then because I.
when you're trying to convince developers to take on security,
it's like trying to encourage your six-year-old to eat the vegetables.
They don't want to.
They don't really you know, they're not really thinking about their health when they get older.
They're thinking about their immediate needs, you know.
Another good analogy I've used is it's it's like selling insurance.
It's protections against something that could possibly happen in the future but might not.
Uh generally people are going to be more focused on what's going to unlock productivity for me now,
you know, what's going to allow me to be more productive.
and move faster.
And so if security is impinging upon that and restricting that,
then it's less likely to get adoption with developers.
We'll move to the next theme which I've already touched on, which is around dependency management.
Can you start off by giving an example of.
or any story where coding assistants have actually introduced dependency management risks?
And how was it found out?
What was the mechanism or what harm could it have caused?
Yes, so we run a system internally at StackHawk,
which scans packages based on there being certain heuristics.
that determine that they are they're more likely to be of risk.
So, they require closer scrutiny.
So, we have this system which uh monitors packages from dependencies from Python PyPI,
crates for Rust, npm for JavaScript, Maven for Java, and there's probably a few others go. as well.
So, we monitor all of these packages and when we see one with suspicious heuristics,
we're able to pull it in and take a closer look.
And we found a good number of malicious packages this way.
One of the ones that our threat researcher found was a believed to be staged by a North.
Korean threat actor, effectively you know, possibly government-sponsored.
And the package in question was used as part of a series of mock fake interviews with developers.
So, they would be contacted on LinkedIn offered a role with a very high-profile,
high-paying company and told, "All you have to do is a coding challenge. Here are the instructions."
And the instructions were to download this package that we found.
And once you download it and execute it by running npm install, it would effectively backdoor your machine.
So, it would it was predominantly focused on Macs,
but your machine would be backdoored and the attackers would start to exfiltrate information to our Telegram server.
And this was, you know, an attack that we found in the wild.
And one of the things we noticed was that we would go to these very,
very, very high-profile cutting-edge, widely used frontier models.
And months later we would say, "Hey, can you tell me how to use this package?"
And it would say, "Sure, yeah, this is certainly this is how to use this package."
And it would generate a code snippet.
And then it would say, "And then run npm install bad package."
And obviously replacing the bad package name here.
And so it was effectively telling people, "Yep, go ahead, use this package.
In fact, here's how to install the package." Which would have resulted in their machines being backdoored. So that was one of the reasons.
that we started to look at introducing this system that could protect people against these malicious packages.
Because it's was quite clear that we were asking some of the top coding assistants,
some of the top models, "Could we use a bad package?"
And it would say, "Certainly you can, and here's how to."
So that was something that we saw quite commonly.
Which was obviously a very, very clear security risk.
And I believe the reason for this was the topic you mentioned about training data being stale.
So LLM had not caught on to the fact that this was a malicious package.
Yes, very much.
And also, a lot of the time when these packages,
these malicious packages are crafted, what they will do is they will choose a name.
that is very close to the name of a popular package.
So for example, there is the the Python package called requests,
which a lot of people use as a HTTP client.
It's very, very widely used. Millions of downloads a week.
And you could take the S and you can maybe switch swap it to a Z,
requests with a Z. Okay?
That's called a typosquatting attack.
The idea is somebody fumbles on a keyboard,
they make a typo, they download and install your package and they're compromised.
Now, the thing is with neural networks,
they're a very, very large collection of vectorized weights and biases, okay?
And how they work is they take natural language and they tokenize it.
And then they perform these multiplication matrix multiplication,
these various math takes place where they calculate the predicted next token.
You know, there's all sorts of things such as a cosine distance,
and they're effectively taking words, breaking them down into these mathematical numbers.
and then they're looking for a close proximity patterns within the neural network. That's probably not the right language to use.
If somebody there's a neural network expert, they'll probably be raising their eyebrows,
but I'm just trying to make this sort of accessible for all.
They find a very similar close proximity matches.
And then they again decode that to natural language.
So, if you make spelling mistakes with an LLM, it often won't mention them.
It won't pull you up on them.
because it knows what you're trying to say.
because it knows of words that are of close proximity to the word. that you've used.
And within the wider context, it's able to match similarity.
It's able to sort of find similar calculations that produce a result of a natural language response.
So, you might have the dog sat on the mat, okay?
It's a very similar mathematically to a very sort of very close set of words.
and letters when tokenized into a neural network.
And so, you can start to see where if you would said to not a neural network.
or to a large language model, "Uh how can I use package name with slight typo?"
it's going to calculate.
Calculate probably not being the right word that you are inferring this particular popular package.
And cuz it's such a popular package, it would have appeared a lot within its training data.
So, the weights and biases would naturally allow it to match to the popular package.
Okay.
So, that's a good example of where large language models are prone to not being aware of typosquatting. attacks, you know.
There's that one that they do quite often.
They say, "How many Rs in strawberry?"
And the LLM is just convinced that it's two.
And you try to convince it it's three, and it just it will not have it.
It's you know, it's to do with this uh vectorization.
They're these huge high-dimensional spaces of these float numbers effectively.
These these vectors and they calculate similar distances around words.
That's how they appear to be human.
So, there's that that's obviously a key risk as well.
On the example that you gave for typosquatting for requests package,
won't the LLM naturally pick up the package which is most popular?
Why would it go and pick a package with a typo or a spelling mistake in it?
Well, interestingly, they do.
That's the interesting thing.
When you do give them a word which is has a slight character difference,
they still will go with that recommendation.
Go with that recommendation is probably not the right way to articulate speaking about a neural network,
but they do go along with the original word that you gave them. I'm not sure why that is.
I mean, you know, these these neural networks, there's a whole study group.
that are trying to figure out what's going on inside them really cuz you know,
there are aspects of them.
that we still don't understand really how they operate certain way,
but it's just a pattern that they they do follow.
Do the security risks differ between companies using proprietary models like GitHub Copilot versus open-source models like Deep. Seek or StarCoder?
Well, good question.
Now, I think we could kind of bring this up a few notches,
where to trust a model, you need to peel back the layers effectively.
So, this is about model provenance, understanding the source of origin of a model.
Okay, so you start with the training data.
Okay, and if there are any risks that are introduced, it's going to be at that stage.
And for the closed-source models, you have no idea of the training data that they use.
You have no idea of the weights.
Okay, so there's very little transparency.
If you make any sort of trust,
it's based on them being an established corporation with a brand to protect, like I spoke about earlier.
Now, open-source models, there are I mean, people call open-source models open-source models,
but there is some nuance to this effectively.
Some models are they have an open license,
so they have an unrestricted license, like Llama, for example, which deems people to label them as open-source.
but they're not really truly open-source in a way,
because the weights are not open or the the data.
that was used to train the model is is not freely available.
So, for you to be able to really trust the model, whether it's open.
or closed, I guess by definition of it being closed,
this would not be possible, you would need to have reproducibility.
You'd need to be able to take the data set, train the model,
and then end up with an identical model.
It's a reproducible training flow. The pipeline is reproducible.
And that is really the only way to be able to 100% trust a model is to have.
that level of provenance, to be able to take all the component parts.
and end up with the same result in large language model.
So, I guess, can you trust open-source models with there being different variations of open-source models?
Perhaps, because there is a bit more transparency.
That is certainly a a factor, but to truly trust the model,
you would need to have the actual training data, as well.
You would need and you would need the computational resources to perform the training,
which, let's be honest, very few of us have.
Now, one of the efforts that is looking to solve this is part of the Six Store project,
which I started a few years ago.
And there is some work around model provenance, which is just kind of 1.0 release.
And this is being used by various people such as Google.
and Nvidia and and other entities are starting to either explore or leverage this form of provenance.
And this consists of cryptographic signing of the different flows of a training pipeline.
So, that you can then get guarantees around the integrity and the provenance of the model.
So, there is some good work going in.
that direction to make these models more accountable and transparent and.
and for you to have some guarantees around the source of origin,
like who did actually train this model?
Is it the person or the people that it claims to originate from?
With a cryptographic provenance, you can get those assurances.
that it is a model that comes from the entity that it claims to have come from.
So, again, this is same problem, same technology that's just rehashed for a new technology.
We we had this for quite a while with container images and packages,
understanding the source of origin, supply chain security, an area that I've I've I've worked in.
for quite a while myself.
All of these technologies have been repurposed for the AI age. So, it's.
It's like any, you know, the old ideas to the new ideas.
All right, and make sure we link to Six Store in our podcast notes.
Sure. Before we wrap up, do you have any thoughts on what's next in AI security?
What are the emerging risks and what are the key mitigating solutions that are being worked on?
That's a very good question.
It's a very good question.
I think a lot of what I've spoken about today are.
yet to really sort of escalate as being problems.
So, I think a lot of what we've touched upon today are some of the future risks.
But, outside of that, I think, you know, the things that are particularly concerning,
and this perhaps goes above security as.
well, is how influential these things are becoming in our lives, okay?
Personal counselors, accountants, they're becoming deeply ingrained in our lives, large language models, and they appear very trustworthy.
The guide rails are working well. Our models seem safe, okay?
But, these models can experience pretty dramatic malfunctions. They really can.
Catastrophic forgetting, overfitting.
These are things that we've seen play out with frontier widely available models,
but there is that intrinsic capacity for a model to really malfunction on a level.
that could completely cause mayhem if other systems are relying on that model for,
you know, automation of infrastructure and the services.
that we rely on to be present every day for society to function.
As LLMs start to become more of a guiding factor in our lives,
the safety of LLMs becomes absolutely critical.
And we we spent some time tuning large language models, trying to tune them to be more security-aware,
and we experienced them go bad robot, and you know.
that it really doesn't take much. You overfit them to a certain degree,
and then suddenly they are just spitting out the same word repeatedly over. and over and over and over.
You're just trying to kill the process to stop it. It's.
It's effectively gone fully to defectual.
So, I think that is a real concern.
AI is creeping more and more into our lives.
You know, we're starting to rely on it.
You're aware of model context protocol?
Have you come across model context protocol?
No, no, I've not. Yeah, okay.
So, model context protocol is a way of providing an interface for an LLM to control machines.
So, an MCP server effectively becomes a tool.
that the LLM is aware of that it can use to interface with other machines and systems.
Okay, so people are producing these MCP servers.
where an LLM can control your Google Drive.
or it can it can create issues and pull requests within a GitHub repository.
or or it could connect to a Jira system and create tickets.
And it's it's a very interesting technology is.
You can see a lot of utility in this.
where LLMs are effectively be able to autonomously interact with systems and automate these processes.
So, they can go beyond just generating code and and engaging with a human,
they can start to control machines.
And that's of course a big concern, you know,
because if these models were to malfunction or to hallucinate and they have the control of machines.
then you can start to see where,
you know, it's it becomes quite obvious where that can be very concerning from a security angle.
And these are technologies that are very much under hype at the moment starting to really get traction,
especially model context protocol.
It's one that's lots of MCP servers coming online to allow you to interface.
and control applications and machines.
These are, you know, they're JavaScript based and not saying that JavaScript's a bad language, but it's a language.
that is a little bit easier to potentially foot gun yourself in regards to security,
web security and so forth.
Like any language, any language can be dangerous if it's used in the wrong way,
but it's, you know, it's an area that's been known for web exploits quite commonly.
You know, it's probably one of the ones that's that's seen more risks manifest than most languages.
I guess because it's web facing.
And so, there's a lot to be concerned around with with this ability for large language models to.
control machines and access APIs and move data around and.
and then of course you have agents.
So agents being these autonomous goal-driven entities.
that are connected to a large language model.
and they are able to go off and with the goal of solving a task.
Effectively, you know, if one of these was to become misaligned or mispurposed,
it could feed false information, it could perform damaging integrations with other systems. There's a lot that could go wrong.
There's a lot that could go wrong.
So yes, very much a brave new world.
that we're entering and I don't think life is going to get any quieter for us security folks. for quite a while.
Absolutely.
Thank you, Luke, for coming on the show. It's been a real pleasure.
This is Bhrijesh Amarnath for Software Engineering Radio.
Thank you for listening.
Thanks for listening to SE Radio, an educational program brought to you by IEEE Software Magazine.
For more about the podcast, including other episodes, visit our website at SE-Radio.net.
To provide feedback, you can comment on each episode on the website or reach us on LinkedIn,
Facebook, Twitter, or through our Slack channel at SE-Radio.slack.com.
You can also email us at team@se-radio.net.
This and all other episodes of SE Radio is licensed under Creative Commons License 2.5.
Thanks for listening.